<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tech | Thijs Lensselink's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://lenss.nl/tag/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lenss.nl/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-27T22:04:26+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://lenss.nl/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Thijs Lensselink]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zend Optimizer+ integrated into 5.5]]></title>
    <link href="http://lenss.nl/2013/02/zend-optimizer%2B-integrated-in-5.5/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-27T22:12:12+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lenss.nl/2013/02/zend-optimizer+-integrated-in-5.5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It looks like PHP is going to get another built in performance boost. The plan is to integrate and open source the <a href="http://files.zend.com/help/previous-version/Zend-Server-4-Community-Edition/zendoptimizerplus.html">Zend Optimizer+</a> component. The fastest Opcode cacher out there. Zend has provided the source. Which is already available on <a href="http://bit.ly/VSsqx3">github</a>. So we get the Opcode cacher to boost  out applications even more. And the community can extend and built upon the available source code. Win! Win!</p>

<p>PHP 5+ has come a long way performance wise without the Optimizer component. But being able to apply opcode cache out of the box is a great addition. And so far the <a href="http://bit.ly/116BnnB">benchmarks</a> look promising. The Optimizer+ component beats <a href="http://pecl.php.net/package/APC">APC</a> hands down in all performed tests.</p>

<p>Read more about Opcode caching and the integration process <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/optimizerplus">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PHPness Serious WTF]]></title>
    <link href="http://lenss.nl/2013/02/phpness-serious-wtf/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-27T11:58:26+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lenss.nl/2013/02/phpness-serious-wtf</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It's been a while since i last blogged. And i don't really have anything new to offer. But i would like to comment on some current event. There has been some commotion about a free t shirt that was distributed on the SunshinePHP conference this year.</p>

<p><a href="http://lenss.nl/images/2013/02/web-and-php-img.png"><img src="http://lenss.nl/images/2013/02/web-and-php-img.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The first time i saw the shirt i could not make out what was so offending that people would start blogging about it. Somebody had to point that out for me. So what's the deal here? Apparently the shirt's slogan was intentionally created with a slight sexual undertone. The idea comes from the enlarge your penis SPAM we all know!</p>

<p>Some people have perceived this as being sexist. And even go so far as to personally attack the people behind the shirt.</p>

<p>Personally i don't think the shirt is sexist or offensive at all. And don't really understand all the fuss. Sex has never been an issue for me in the PHP community. I learn just as much from female developers as i do from the male ones. We are all equal. People that feel the need to defend the opposite sex are probably the ones that see a difference. Even so! Why make such a big deal of something so small? I never seen anybody blog about the programming with attitude poster.</p>

<p><a href="http://lenss.nl/images/2013/02/php-programming.jpg"><img src="http://lenss.nl/images/2013/02/php-programming.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>I think the PHP community has just lost a bit of it's shine and coolness. I've always been under the impression the PHP community consisted of free thinking people that do what they love. Develop stuff. And that's exactly what attracted me to it 12 years ago in the first place.</p>

<p>The community has grown quite a lot in that period of time. The thing with every communities is that it brings forth vocal people. Which is a great thing in general. But not so good when people forget their responsibility towards the rest of the community. And that's exactly what happened the last few days. Personal issues have become public. To me it seems many of you have missed the boat completely. You don't have to like the shirt. But there is absolutely no reason to bash the initiative in public.</p>

<p>Here are some of the articles the spawned over the last couple days:</p>

<p><a href="http://webandphpmag.wordpress.com/2013/02/25/phpness-gate-raising-interesting-issues/">PHPness Gate – raising interesting issues</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.brandonsavage.net/on-public-outrage-and-bad-actors/">On Public Outrage And Bad Actors</a></p>

<p><a href="http://caseysoftware.com/blog/sexism-php-community">Sexism in the PHP Community</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.leftontheweb.com/message/On_SexismRacismAnyotherism_and_the_PHP_Community">On Sexism/Racism/Any-other-ism and the PHP Community</a></p>

<p><a href="http://blog.calevans.com/2013/02/22/sexism-and-php/">Sexism and PHP</a></p>

<p><a href="http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=5269120">Hacker news - Sexism and PHP (calevans.com)</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.gogolek.co.uk/blog/2013/02/web-and-php-sexist-tshirt-debate-my-2-cents/">Web &amp; PHP sexist tshirt debate – my 2 cents</a></p>

<p><a href="http://blog.ircmaxell.com/2013/02/on-equality-sexism-and-even-hand.html">On Equality, Sexism and an Even Hand</a></p>

<p>So let's all just respect one another. And keep the PHP community a friendly place. This kind of nonsense has no positive impact on anybody.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Publish Google Reader shared items]]></title>
    <link href="http://lenss.nl/2012/11/publish-google-reader-shared-items/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-07T15:55:26+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lenss.nl/2012/11/publish-google-reader-shared-items</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A lot of people are using the shared items feature in <a href="http://www.google.nl/reader/">Google Reader</a> to publish what they are reading on a blog. It's like having a live blogroll widget on your website. And gives your readers a good impression of what you are actually interested in.</p>

<p>I never bothered adding this to my blog. But i do like to share. So last night i was trying to figure out how to integrate this with my current blog. I was hoping for an easy implementation. But the information is scarce. So i had to do some digging. I did find a couple of <a href="https://www.google.nl/search?q=wordpress+plugin+google+reader">Wordpress plugins</a>. But most of them were not updated for at least a year. And i am not putting code like that life on my website.</p>

<p>After some Googling i came across a couple of feed URL's that seem to share their <strong>shared</strong> items in feed form. Using the Google Reader URL and a user id. So the URL for my shared items would look like the one below. Getting your user id by the way is easy. Go to your Google reader page. Click all <strong>All items</strong> and the <strong>UID</strong> will show up in the address bar.</p>

<blockquote><p>http://www.google.com/reader/shared/16525759780220726764</p></blockquote>

<p>The problem with this however. Non of my shared posts show up on this page. And i have not figured out a way to populate it just yet. So i came up with an other path to get this data on my server.</p>

<p>In the Google Reader pages it's possible to add sharing functionality. This is done by going to the <strong>Send To</strong> tab</p>

<p><a href="http://lenss.nl/images/2012/11/Send-To.png"><img src="http://lenss.nl/images/2012/11/Send-To-300x22.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>From here it's possible to select a service to share data with. Non of these services are any good for what i am trying to do. But the great thing about this page is. You can provide custom URL's for sharing data. Just incorporate the specified parameters in the URL and your done.</p>

<p><a href="http://lenss.nl/images/2012/11/Custom-Site.png"><img src="http://lenss.nl/images/2012/11/Custom-Site-300x178.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Once configured and saved a custom URL is visible in the <strong>Send To</strong> panel</p>

<p><a href="http://lenss.nl/images/2012/11/Favorite-Site.png"><img src="http://lenss.nl/images/2012/11/Favorite-Site-300x125.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>That's it for this part. Actually sharing items is quite easy now. When back in the Google Reader under each post there is Send to link. If you click this link the newly created custom URL will show up. And you can share the post.</p>

<p><a href="http://lenss.nl/images/2012/11/Tag-Article.png"><img src="http://lenss.nl/images/2012/11/Tag-Article-300x41.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The only thing left to do is write some code to process the incoming data. To get you started. Some of the code i used while testing this is posted below</p>

<pre><code>Class GoogleReaderShare
{
    const GOOGLE_REMOTE_IP = '95.97.54.3';

    const GOOGLE_REFERER = 'http://www.google.nl/reader/view/';

    protected static $_whitelist = array('source', 'title', 'url', 'short');

    public static function CheckSource($remoteAddr, $referer) 
    {
        if (($remoteAddr == self::GOOGLE_REMOTE_IP) 
                &amp;&amp; ($referer == self::GOOGLE_REFERER)) {
            return true;
        }
        return false;
    }

    protected static function _CheckIncomingData($data)
    {
        if (!is_array($data)) {
            return false;
        }

        foreach ($data as $key =&gt; $value) {
            if (!in_array($key, self::$_whitelist)) {
                return false;
            }
        }
    }

    public static function Process($data) 
    {
        if (!self::_CheckIncomingData($data)) {
            throw new Exception("Unrecognized or no incoming data");
        }

        // process the data
    }
}

if (GoogleReaderShare::CheckSource($_SERVER['REMOTE_ADDR'], $_SERVER['HTTP_REFERER'])) {
    GoogleReaderShare::Process($_GET);
}
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Long running PHP script and MySQL server gone away]]></title>
    <link href="http://lenss.nl/2012/10/long-running-php-script-and-mysql-server-gone-away/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-29T14:39:26+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://lenss.nl/2012/10/long-running-php-script-and-mysql-server-gone-away</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the moment i am writing some workers that interact with a <a href="http://kr.github.com/beanstalkd/">beanstalk</a> server. When data gets pushed into the beanstalk server. My workers will be triggered to process this data. So the workers are sitting idle for most of the time. And just wait for some data to process. No rocket science there. But during testing i kept running into <a href="http://www.mysql.com/">MySQL</a> issues. The script seemed to lose connection to the MySQL server when it was idle for longer then a minute. And would respond with a</p>

<blockquote><p>Warning: <a href="http://php.net/mysql_query">mysql_query</a>(): MySQL server has gone away in /path/to/some/mysql4/class.php on line xxx</p></blockquote>

<p>So whats going on here? Well actually it's quite simple. When my script initializes the database connection it doesn't use it. It just sits there waiting for incoming data. Once received it will process it and try to store it in the database. But when the waiting period exceeds the time for PHP to keep the MySQL connection open it responds with the warning mentioned above. Now in previous versions of PHP this would not be a big issue. As PHP would just initiate a reconnect when the connection is lost. But from PHP 5.0.3 and up this functionality has been disabled by default. For MySQLI this is no problem at all.</p>

<p>MySQLi:</p>

<blockquote><p>mysqli.reconnect = Off to On</p></blockquote>

<p>Unfortunately i am working with PHP's core mysql_* functions (don't get me started) and there doesn't seem to be an easy way to resolve this. According to the MySQL documentation</p>

<pre><code>mysql_options(&amp;mysql;, MYSQL_OPT_RECONNECT, &amp;reconnect;);
</code></pre>

<p>Should do the trick. But passing <strong>MYSQL_OPT_RECONNECT</strong> in anyway to <a href="http://php.net/mysql_connect">mysql_connect</a> didn't result in the result i was looking for. So what now? Porting the database code to make use of the newer and better PDO or MySQLi is no option. As it would consume way to much time. Fortunately the mysql_* core functions come with mysql_ping. I never had to use this before. But in this case it comes in quite handy.</p>

<p><strong>From the PHP manual:</strong></p>

<pre><code>bool mysql_ping ([ resource $link_identifier = NULL ] )
</code></pre>

<blockquote><p>Checks whether or not the connection to the server is working. If it has gone down, an automatic reconnection is attempted. This function can be used by scripts that remain idle for a long while, to check whether or not the server has closed the connection and reconnect if necessary.</p></blockquote>

<p>Note:
<strong>Automatic reconnection is disabled by default in versions of MySQL >= 5.0.3.</strong></p>

<p>Adding the mysql_ping function call was rather straight forward. And didn't require all that much work to be done. I extended the database class to include a ping method. That would simply throw an exception when it failed to reconnect.</p>

<pre><code>public function ping()
{
    if (!mysql_ping($this-&gt;db_connect_id)) {
        throw new Mollie_Database_Exception("Connection was lost");
    }   
    return true;
}
</code></pre>

<p>And after that i started poking around the userland implementation. The worker is running inside a <strong>while(true)</strong> loop. A first test with <strong>->ping()</strong> being called inside this loop proved to resolve the issue at hand. But running the ping function that often is overkill. And who knows it might actually result in <strong>DoS</strong> of the database server. So i decided to ping the server every one minute or so.</p>

<pre><code>$start = time();
while (true) 
{
    $this-&gt;_keepConnectionAlive($start);
</code></pre>

<p>And the keepConnectionAlive method looks something like this</p>

<pre><code>protected function _keepConnectionAlive(&amp;$start)
{
    $passed = (time() - $start);
    if ($passed &gt; 60)
    {
        $start = time();
        $this-&gt;_db-&gt;ping();
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>I'm not a big fan of this solution. And would rather be implementing MySQLi functions. But this functions well. And will do for now.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git: Rebase on pull by default]]></title>
    <link href="http://lenss.nl/2012/10/git-rebase-on-pull-by-default/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-25T14:20:22+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://lenss.nl/2012/10/git-rebase-on-pull-by-default</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was a bit surprised today when <a href="http://git-scm.com/">git</a> presented me a merge message window after i did a pull. This should not happen as the normal behavior here should be to <a href="http://git-scm.com/book/en/Git-Branching-Rebasing">rebase</a> the changes. But apparently that didn't happen this time. When i asked one of the other <a href="http://www.scriptorama.nl/">dev</a> 's what could be the issue. We quickly figured out i was just missing some <strong>config</strong> entry in <strong>.git/config</strong>. This probably happened some time ago when i did a fresh checkout.</p>

<p>So to make sure rebasing is done by default. You can run a simple git command or modify the <strong>.git/config</strong> file manually.</p>

<blockquote><p>$ git config branch.autosetuprebase always</p></blockquote>

<p>or do</p>

<blockquote><p>$ vi .git/config</p></blockquote>

<p>Make sure <strong>[branch "master"]</strong> has <strong>rebase</strong> set to true. It should look like the snippet below.</p>

<blockquote><p>[branch "master"]</p>

<pre><code>remote = origin
merge = refs/heads/master
rebase = true
</code></pre></blockquote>

<p>Starting to really like git. A couple of more quirks and things will be running fine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
